CURICULUM VITAE

MR. JOASH SANGARA AMINGA

P. O. Box 74434 - 00200 City Square, Nairobi

Tel: 0722 605048 or 0763 605048 Office (DL): 020 3247196

E-mail: joashsan@gmail.com or joashsan@yahoo.com

DATE OF BIRTH: 21ST JANUARY 1967

Biography

Joash S. Aminga is a career Information Science practitioner pursuing a Doctor of Philosophy in Information Science and has a Master of Philosophy in Information Sciences (Library & Information Studies), Bachelor of Science in Information Management, Diploma in Information Studies, Library Assistants' Certificate and, an Accredited Knowledge Management Consultancy Certificate. Mr. Aminga has over thirty two (32) years of working experience with different Institutions/Organizations and in various capacities. He has attended and participated in various leadership, senior management courses, conferences, seminars and workshops where he has also presented papers. He is an active member of the Association of Government Librarians (AGL); Kenya Association of Records Management (KARMA); Information & Records Management Society (IRMS) and, Chartered Institute of Professional Management (CIPM). His research interests include effective resource sharing, Knowledge Management, access /use of e-resources and, creating platforms for addressing organized information. He is currently serving as an Assistant Director, Records/Library Services with the Office of the Deputy President.

Education

- 2016 Student of Doctor of Philosophy in Information Sciences (Library & Information Studies)
 Kisii University
- **2012** Master of Philosophy in Information Sciences (Library & Information Studies) Moi University
- 2005 BSc Degree in Information Management

Bronte International University

1999 Certificate in Computer Operations

Ruki Commercial College

- 1996 Diploma in Information Studies
 Kenya School of Professional Studies
- 1988 Library Assistants' Certificate

The Kenya Polytechnic

1984 Kenya Certificate of Education

Kisii High School

1980 Certificate of Primary Education

Nyaura Primary School

Current Position and Salary:

Assistant Director, Records/Library Services (w.e.f 4th November 2015 to-date)

Office of the Deputy President

P.O. Box 74434 - 00200 City Square, **Nairobi**

Tel. 020 3247196

Current duties and responsibilities

- Responsible for coordinating efficient and effective Records and Library services for timely and accurate information
- Dissemination of information to relevant officers in a timely manner
- ♣ Implementation of Records /Library policies, selection procedures and acquisition of information materials.
- ♣ Preparation and compilation of various documents, reports and briefing materials for visiting teams/Consultants and for the Deputy President and,
- **♣** Information dissemination and preparation of user profiles
- ♣ Conducting quick reference searches, retrieving information and identifying library user needs alongside effective sharing of information with relevant stakeholders and, responding to inquiries,
- ♣ Developing/managing Library collection, processing and identifying relevant articles for scanning and digitization
- 🖶 Ensuring good organizational safety and healthy working environment
- ♣ Effective management of Library and records management unit's assets
- ♣ Managing and controlling Library expenditure (budget) and, responsible for formulation of the Records /Library management services strategic plan

Employment history

Jun 2011 - Apr. 2013: Principal Librarian - Office of the Prime Minister

Nov. 2010 - May 2011: Chief Librarian - Ministry of Justice, National Cohesion & Const. Affairs

June 2009 - Oct 2010: Senior Librarian - Committee of Experts on the Constitution (Seconded)

July 2007 - May 2009: Senior Librarian- Ministry of Justice & Constitutional Affairs

June 2006 - June 2007: Librarian I - Ministry of Trade and Industry

March - May 2006: Librarian - Committee of Eminent Persons (Seconded)

Mar 2002 - Feb 2006: Programme Officer - Constitution of Kenya Review Commission (Seconded)

Nov 1990 - Feb 2002: Senior Library Assistant - Ministry of Trade and Industry

June 1989 - Oct 1990: Library Assistant I - Kenya Science Teachers College

Jan 1986 - May 1989: Library Assistant II - Kisii High School

Internship

Sept - December 1994: Internship and attachment – UNEP, Library & Documentation Centre, Gigiri

Courses attended

- **2018 Digital Records Preservation Training** KARMA/ ICA Africa Programme Commission
- **2017 ISO 9001:2015 Quality Management Systems (QMS) Training -** Millennium Management Consultants Ltd (MMCAfrica)
- 2017 Library Training on KOHA Records and Information Management East Africa (RIMEA) Ltd
- 2016 Cyber-Security Awareness Training -Office of the Deputy President, held in Nairobi
- **2014** Strategic Leadership Development Programme Kenya School of Government (KSG)
- 2014 Standardization of Technical Processing of Information Resources in Government Libraries in Kenya Ministry of Culture, Sports and the Arts
- 2013 Electronic Document Management Systems & Paperless Office LAPTRUST

- 2012 Accredited Knowledge Management Consultant Knowledge Management Associates
- **2012 Senior Management Course** Kenya Institute of Administration (KIA).
- **2012** Management Skills Development Government Training Institute (GTI) Baringo
- **2009** Public Procurement & Disposal Act, 2005 & Regulations 2006 Kenya Institute of Supplies Management
- 2008 Peace Building and Conflict Management MS-Training for Development Co-operation, Arusha
- **2007** Wider Role of a Volunteer Pre-departure course Volunteer Services Organization (VSO)
- 2003 Strategic Document Management systems Records & Archives Management Systems (RAMS)
- 2001 Trainer of Trainers on HIV & AIDS Min. of Tourism, Trade & Industry/NACC
- 1997 Disaster Management & Emergency Conditions in Community Based First Aid Kenya Red Cross
- 1997 Information Acquisition/Dissemination for Industrial growth-ARCEDM/KIRDI

Seminars, Workshops and Conferences attended

- 2018 Annual Records & Information Management Professionals East Africa (RIMPEA) Conference
 Records & Information Management East Africa (RIMEA) held at Milele Beach Hotel, Mombasa
- **2017 Promoting Information Integrity and Accountability in the Public Service -** Association of Government Librarians, held at Burch's Resort, Naivasha
- 2017 Records & Information Management Professionals East Africa (RIMPEA) Conference
 Records & Information Management East Africa (RIMEA) held at Naivasha Panorama Park Hotel
- **2017** 1st National Conference on Records Management and Good Governance Kenya Association of Records Management (KARMA), held at Plaza Beach Hotel-Mombasa
- 2017 Information as a tool for enhancing implementation of Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)in the Public Service Association of Government Librarians, held in Eldoret
- 2016 Records & Knowledge Management workshop Records & Information Management, East Africa Limited (RIMEA), held in Naivasha Panorama Park Hotel
- **2016** Information and Devolution in achieving the Kenya Vision 2030 **Association of Government Librarians**, held in Mombasa
- 2016 Digital Transformation and changing role of Libraries and Information Centres in the sustainable development of Africa- 22nd Standing Conference of Eastern, Central & Southern African Library & Information Associations (SCESCAL, XXII), held in Swaziland
- 2015 "Information as a Tool for Good Governance and Economic Empowerment Association of Government Librarians held in Kisumu
- **2014** Information Literacy: a bridge to management and use of e-resources **Kenya Library Association**, held in Eldoret
- **2014** The 21st Century information Managers: Making Kenya a knowledge-based society **Association of Government Librarians,** held in Kisumu
- 2013 Transforming Government, National Assembly, Judiciary and State Corporation Libraries into Digital Centres of Innovation and Development - Association of Government Librarians, held in Mombasa
- **2013** Building and Managing Strong Libraries and Information Service Centres through Creativity, Innovation and ICT **Kenya Library Association**, held in Nairobi

- **2012** Government, National Assembly, Judiciary & State Corporation Libraries: Challenges & Opportunities in 21st Century- **Association of Government Librarians**, held in Mombasa
- 2012 Information for Sustainable Development in a Digital Environment 20th Standing Conference of Eastern, Central & Southern African Library & Information Associations (SCESCAL, XX), held in Nairobi
- **2011** The Constitution of Kenya & use of Government Information Centres **Association of Government Librarians**, held in Kisumu
- 2006 Automation of E-Government policies in Information & Resource Centres in 21st Century in Kenya
 Association of Government Librarians / Moi University, held in Eldoret

Papers presented

- Access to Information Act in Reference to the Constitution of Kenya (2010) Presented during the 2018 Annual Records & Information Management Professionals East Africa (RIMPEA) Conference held from 17th to 21st September 2018 at Milele Beach Hotel, Mombasa
- Access to Information Act in Reference to the Constitution of Kenya (2010) Presented during the Association of Government Librarians Conference held at Burch's Resort, Naivasha in October, 2017
- ◆ Office Automation Presented during the 2017 Annual Records & Information Management Professionals East Africa (RIMPEA) Conference held from 26th to 29th September 2017 at held at Lake Naivasha Panorama Park Hotel
- **Development of Professional Library Associations** presented during the Association of Government Librarians Conference/AGM held from 1st − 3rd March 2017, at The Pearl Hotel, Eldoret
- **A Study of Knowledge Management processes and the role of Tacit and Explicit Knowledge in the Workplace** presented during the Association of Government Librarians Annual Conference held from 26th 31st October 2014 at Metropak Hotel, Kisumu
- Libraries as platforms of Economic Prosperity: Transforming lives of Kenyans presented during the Association of Government Librarians Annual Conference held from 10th 17th November 2013 at Bridge Hotel, Mombasa
- **Strategic Management and Budgeting in Libraries** presented during the Association of Government Librarians Annual Conference held from 10^{th -} 17th November 2013 at Bridge Hotel, Mombasa
- Repackaging and Marketing Library and Information Services presented during the Association of Government Librarians Annual Conference held from 28th October ⁻ 3rd November 2013 at Darajani Hotel, Mombasa

Key achievements and Recognition

- **Certificate of Appreciation** for Presenting a paper on Access to Information during the 2018 RIMPEA Conference at Milele Beach Hotel, Mombasa
- **Certificate of Recognition** for presenting a paper on Access to Information Act in Reference to the Constitution of Kenya (2010) at Burch's Resort, Naivasha
- **Certificate of Appreciation** as a Guest Speaker during the RIMEA EDMS Training, Nairobi
- Appraisal and archiving of records relating to the former Office of the Prime Minister with the Kenya National Archives & Documentation Services for research and historical posterity
- **Commendation** for role played in Office of the Prime Minister's ISO 9001:2008 Certification

- **Appraisal and archiving of records** relating to Constitutional review process in Kenya
- **Member of the Secretariat** to the Committee of Experts on the Constitutional Review Process
- **Member of the Secretariat** to the Committee of Eminent Persons on the Constitutional Review
- Member of the Secretariat to the Constitution of Kenya Review Commission (Research, Drafting & Tech. Support)
- **Member of the Secretariat** to the National Constitutional Conference (Bomas I, II, & III),
- **Commendation** for role played in Micro-teaching at the Kenya Science Teachers College

Professional competencies

- Participated in the preparation of the Records Management Policy for the Office of the Deputy President
- Experience in knowledge planning for computerized Library and information resource centres for comprehensive knowledge management initiatives and strategies,
- Designing and implementing knowledge learning infrastructures,
- # Effective management of Email and Internet search services and responding to client queries online through the use of various platforms
- ♣ Strategic document management as well as efficient filing systems and retrieval of data requests
- Conducting the production of reports, journals, newsletters, pamphlets and brochures/flyers for outreach programmes and training through organized workshops/seminars and, conferences,
- Communication skills in presenting information (oral, written & online)
- ♣ Supervisory skills, interpersonal skills & ability to establish and maintain effective working relations,
- Literacy in computer operations and use of standard Microsoft Office products,
- Team player with the ability to meet demanding deadlines

Key experiences

- ♣ Effective training in searching for information and dissemination
- ♣ Knowledge of various Library Automation software, systems and use of various Library Schemes
- ♣ Background support in HIV & AIDS programmes,
- Use and application of KOHA, AACR2 and MARC technology,
- Proficiency in various Information Technology issues and trends in modern libraries including the role of ICTs in accessing knowledge management tools which include computerized data systems
- Experience in holding public forums and exhibitions to promote public awareness and conducting Civic Education.

Membership of Professional Association

- ♣ Member of the Kenya Association of Record Managers and Archivists (KARMA-0374)
- ♣ Member of the Association of Government Librarians in Kenya (AGL- 057)
- ♣ Member of the Information & Records Management Society (IRMS-5602)
- ♣ Member of the Chartered Institute of Professional Management (CIPM4871)
- ♣ Member of the Records a& Information Management Professionals in East Africa (RIMPEA/KE/0201)

Extra-curricular and social activities

- ♣ Volunteer Services (Branch Secretary, Kenya Red Cross Society, Nakuru Branch in 1997/1998)
- Counseling and Training
- ♣ Video Recording and Photography

Publications

- **Aminga, J. S. (2016).** A Study on Knowledge Management Processes in the Workplace **A** Chapter in the Book Library Science: Emerging Concepts and Innovation By Dr Somvir (ed)
- Aminga, J. S. (2015). Quality Management in Environment, Workplace Culture and Management, Munich, GRIN Publishing GmbH, http://www.grin.com/en/e-book/292814/quality-management-in-environment-workplace-culture-and-management ISBN (eBook) 978-3-656-90043-6
- **Aminga, J. S.** (2012). Prospects for resource-sharing among Government Libraries in Nairobi (Thesis), GRIN Publishing. ISBN(eBook) 978-3-656-88203-9

Referees

1. Ms. Beverly C. Moss

Secretary, Conflict Management & Peace Building Office of the Deputy President P. O. Box 74434 – 00200 **Nairobi**

Tel. 0722 709259

Email: beverlykoech@gmail.com

2. Ms Bahati Keranga Mwita

Director, Corporate Services Kenya Water Towers Agency P. O. Box 42903 – 00100 **Nairobi**

Tel. 0722744491

Email: keranga@yahoo.com

3. Mr. Richard Atuti

Director/CEO Kenya National Library Services P. O. Box 30573 – 00100, **Nairobi Tel.** 0728607628

Email: richard.atuti@knls.ac.ke